so let's say that someone has been
reading the sutas and they
have a small or large amount of clarity
regarding what the Buddhist teaching is
um they're able to explain it to others
they're able to explain it to themselves
everything makes sense and
um and
yet if they ask themselves
honestly um whether they're still
whether they're free from suffering or
whether they're still subject to
suffering it becomes clear that they
aren't so what is it then that
so what is it then that
um needs to improve or or evolve further
for that information that a person has
to
become an Insight the direct Insight
that actually liberates
them yeah how to move from ideas from
the right ideas to Insight mhm
mhm I guess guess a lowball kind of
approach to that would be to say well
the ideas you have are you applying them
to the extent that you understand
them so what would be one common idea
that um you know every Buddhist
knows but might not apply for example
like you know what you might not know
what greed means in like the truest most
kind of enlightened sense but you have
some idea of what greed is that aligns
with your own experience so are you
giving into that when it arises or are
you not giving into it I guess that can
be one Avenue
of questioning
for so um because the thing is the the
the people would um become content
become content
with where the point where they had
reached because they would have realized
that a change has factually occurred
compared to
um very often a change has occurred in
terms of
um well their opinions like they they
their opinions about things
were reflecting back to where they were
would become clear that they were very
wrong in the past compared to what it
would be now just on account of the
information but the crucial distinction
there is that um having an
opinion in line with the teaching for
example um in the sutas you would
see opinions that are very clearly not
in line with the suas like the
Aesthetics of other sects when they
would go around saying
that um there is no K there is no there
is no action there is no uhhuh
um fruits and results of good and bad
actions there is no mother there is no
father uh or in a modern sense you might
have people adhering to I don't know
nism or uh you know various sort of
worldly ideologies and you feel factually that
ideologies and you feel factually that
you've been able to affect the change
from that to let's say now your belief
is anata you believe in anata you
believe in the four noble truths you
believe in K you believe in Freedom from
suffering and whatnot but the thing is
those are opinions or those are beliefs
and uh view is something different well
not necessarily different but something
deeper than that so you can the point
being changing your opinion is necessary
for you to begin the
practice in the first place but your
view has not necessarily changed and the
measurement of of your view changing
is what is
it yeah yeah but that like what is the
uh criteria for for that which we just
mentioned oh well you you need to hear
the true teaching and criteria for
defining what is like because again you
you have the same opinion like you still
you you also believe that uh there is
suffering there is that craving is the
origin of suffering that the session of
suffering is the escape and now you're
asking what's the difference between
believing that yes and actually a noble
disciple realizing the vulnerable truth
right well you see belief is something
colloquially speaking you're not quite
sure like something could be the case
but you're not 100% sure mhm you might
have good reasons to believe a certain
thing and most of the time you can
conduct yourself based on that belief
but that belief will always be bound up
with a sense of Doubt Bel and doubt go
together but now when the Buddha talks
about right view that doesn't go
together with that doubt which is on the
side of belief So Right View has that
confidence or that certainty and that is
a distinction that we can make it seems
to me between what is actually right
view the S of the sutas and the belief
um the way people collo use like belief
yeah so okay that's one angle from which
you could approach it which we can come
back to later but um so how does it feel
what is the the most
um because a person might again you you
might have studied Buddhism for so long
and for 20 30 years that you kind of
feel like you don't have doubts about
this anymore like some of it might even
have been confirmed learn by
random you know little insights that you
had here and there oh I see and uh and
you can you can kind of convince
yourself I mean with mad people like you
yeah they don't um admit the fact that
they're still subject to doubt yeah well
so then we have to come back to our
discussion on authenticity like people
need to be honest with themselves am I
still liable to suffering yeah so that's
it so the the um right the criteria for
who is a soap or not
more than just asking what how sure am I
of this because you know many kind of uh
can yourself like okay I'm I'm I'm very
sure but you might have not considered
something yeah exactly and so later on
you might still be shaken yeah yeah so
many people can be expressed like you
know insane amounts of of certainty in
regards to various things but the right
view is measured by obviously yes you
need some degree of authenticity but
more practically
are you um still liable to
suffering on in in any shape or form
like if you if you ask yourself do you
still uh depend on on um certain coping
mechanisms or certain strategies for you
to escape that suffering and at the same
time you think that uh you're free from
doubt like you have truly understood
that craving is the root of suffering
well that doesn't go together you you
wouldn't have any need to to run away
from suffering in that sense if you have
understood the Escape so that's one of
the clear signs that what you have more
is a is a belief or or is an opinion and
your view is still not in line with with
the Buddhist teaching fundamentally so
um so back to what you said about doubt
um so what is it that would then turn a
belief the same opinion or the same
belief that you started from so it's not
that it changes like you you hear um the
teaching of the Buddha and and it's in
the content like the the phrasing and
the and the the expression is the same
it's not like there was some hidden um
stanza or or something that you would
now come up with that you could have
before it's more um well what is it what
what's the difference what is it that
makes that belief turn into something
that it's uh impossible to doubt
mhm well it's got to be all
encompassing view because if it isn't
there's room for
doubt yes of course but um how do you
make it all
s well that has got to do with the yonar
yeah so um we can so that's exactly why
the uh this s to say there's two
conditions for the arising of the Right
View uhuh one of them is the utterance
of another through which you change your
opinion you could say from the very
start but if you don't have y then all
you're left with is the utterance of
another that now became your utterance
but it doesn't necessarily mean that it
became integrated let's say St it stays
on the level of ideas like you might
genuinely hear something new or somebody
might confirm something that you already
believed and now you are more certain
and you agree with it and you agree with
it and so you now have more certainty
like oh this other person that I have
great faith in says the same thing but
that's still not it yeah or or even
again you you had a completely wrong
opinion you changed it but um if if that
liability to doubt and suffering is
still there it hasn't permeated like you
said it hasn't become
all-encompassing so that it becomes a
view now
now
um what so let's say
uh common example craving is suffering
that's a belief or or the root of
suffering is craving that's a belief or
an opinion that almost every Buddhist
might have but why is it not
all-encompassing without just going to
the um textbook answer of
Y well that has to be a a suit basis
let's say in one's experience
for those statements to land so to speak
so if someone is living a life that is
rooted by a large in acting out of
craving then you can need someone who
expect your de free from craving and who
tells you that craving is suffering and
then you might still agree with that on
on the level of ideas failing to see
that that's completely disconnected from
how you from how you conduct yourself in
your daily life so that
discrepancy um has to end in so that it
creates let's say a basis for that idea
to land so that it becomes an Insight
that doesn't leave anything out yeah so
so that would be obviously again the
first step um so you you
hear it becomes even more of a empty
opinion if you're if if you quote
unquote believe in it but but your
day-to-day action are totally um based
on
other uh assumptions that that that are
contrary to that uh so let's say then
that you have restrained your
living to the best of your ability to to
to the point where you're aware you live
according to the idea or belief that you
acquired that uh craving is the root of
suffering and you never do anything that
you know is rooted in craving um
but then so what what is left there
right well this is I was going to say
like this discrepancy that you mentioned
you still you can kind of take that
principle I guess and keep going with
it in so far as if
you have the opinions but your
views like you can tell okay I'm not
free from suffering so My Views aren't
quite aligned with my opinions that
means I believe believe something that I
don't
actually like I I I say that I believe
something but I don't actually I guess
you could put it that way
so trying
to kind of recognize okay there's there
is a discrepancy somewhere
like what I guess one one example that's
what I guess one one example that's
probably super super common for most
most kind of most Buddhists is getting
so used to just like denying oh no
there's no self no self no self being
able to actually kind of say like okay
well let's stop dismissing that and
actually look for like clearly I have
self viw so kind of letting that
manifest in your experience not just
pushing it away because it's wrong it's
not in line with your belief um cuz if
it was your view you wouldn't have to do
that yeah that's one one important point
you need to be willing
to accept and that that um feeds back
into that
authenticity willing to accept that you
still have the fundamental
illness you might
have uh found like the belief is on the
level of oh look that's the best best
doctor over there mhm and and that's
your belief and it's accurate but if you
don't uh go through with the treatment
which will be painful because you know
it's it's requir you to accept that you
are sick it's no longer just an
impersonal um acknowledgement of how
great the doctor is it's now about you
and your condition yeah so um it
requires you then to have that
authenticity to say yes it doesn't
matter how much I agree with all the
the theory of of that this doctor talks
about of of how to cure this disease
fundamentally I am still not cured yeah
so ironically you have to start by
taking it quite personally yeah that's
it so if you use the beliefs to kind of
cover up your wrong
view that's that's one of the main uh
obstacles cuz then you you
will the belief is supposed to like that
external utterance of another is
supposed to be
um for the lack of a better word applied
to the wrong understanding that you have
which means you need to have admitted to
yourself that that wrong understanding
is there and that wrong understanding
will be um sort of
indirectly brought to the surface by the
presence of suffering so if if you don't
allow suffering to arise to begin with
like as as he said your first response
is to get rid of it then you have
nothing for the belief to ironically
apply to like there's no work for you to
do really um which is but in a wrong way
like instead of no work to do because
you got to the end it's like no work to
do because you're refusing to start yeah
you just uh kind of uh like content with
just pointing to where the goal is but
not walking there yourself mhm so that's
the um the the admission that has to
come first like because yeah I um I
understand or I have the the view the
opinion or the belief
that um the five Aggregates are
impermanent that they're suffering that
they're not self but my view is
different because if it wouldn't be you
would at least be and and you wouldn't
have all the suffering that you're
having clearly so um then the the right
place for that belief you you will start
to see that that information that you
have is not just something for you to
like hold as a trophy or something it's
it's it's the stuff that you have to use
like a like a like an like I don't know
like a shovel that you need to use in
order to be digging yeah digging with a
knife yeah oh yeah yeah deling or
digging with a knife yeah yeah and it's
through that belief or that opinion it's
telling you kind of where you're going
to go
but if you're just again satisfied with
the content of the of the belief or the
view uh you're not going to be using it
for the purpose that it actually is
meant to to fulfill so um the other
thing as well is the liability to doubt
is
um like you will never transcend doubt
by improving the opinion or improving
the information to some theoretically
perfect point it's precisely by
recognizing well you would only be able
to do that again if you have admitted to
yourself that you're still liable to
suffering and then you realize what is
doubt like what is what is actually
doubt is a doubt that I that my um
opinion or or information is not
perfectly extensive and comprehensive or
is a doubt that when my information or
uh beliefs are not comprehensive enough
I resist that
discomfort and then on that level you'll
be able to now apply the information
that craving is suffering and you would
overcome doubt through that Avenue not
by getting you know perfect definitions
of the of the I don't know 115 types of
suffering that correspond to the craving
in such and such sense base or something
like some sort of Abid analysis it would
be a concrete application of that belief
in okay there is doubt there is
unpleasantness and discomfort in account
of that doubt and I know that anything
that I do rooted in um craving against
the discomfort of that doubt will be
ironically against well will be
perpetuating the wrong view that it's
the discomfort that is the suffering not
the resistance to it so see you have the
same belief on paper craving his
suffering and you will be applying It
Grow uh in a way that's actually growing
the wrong
view because you you you still imply
that it's on some level you imply I am
suffering because I'm not clear enough
about how craving his suffering on the
level of information and you don't see
that it's actually uh well that's what
where y would come in yeah you don't see
that it's actually you here and now in
regards to that lack of knowledge
resisting that discomfort that is your
failure the other thing I want to say is
so that uh craving that you have in
relation to not knowing the answer to
something um
it needs to be kind of the information
is not applied to sort of get rid of it
which again would be falling into that
um misapplication of the information to
basically like deny the fact that you're
sick as quickly as possible it's uh as
we keep saying it's for you
to practically speaking be able to
endure that discomfort so if you still
have a background assumption that
information is sort of meant for the
purpose of dealing with discomfort in in
that direct sense like um knocking it
off then uh that's going to be again
still proliferating the same wrong view
um yeah so the doctor can prescribe
medicine and say these pills two times a
day those pills five times a day you can
have all that information if you don't
take them it's not going to make any
difference yeah well or or or you take
them when you want to take them yeah
yeah you don't take them in
the so
the the development of uh
Y how does it start
start
uhhuh which is so that you know mixed
with that information you have it can
become the right
or let's put it this way
um what do the sutas Define is the
progression towards uh the purification of
you what do the sutas Define as the
progression towards or the prerequisites
for the purification of
here say needs to happen first before
one's views can be purified
uhhuh gradual training
yeah yeah but which means what in this
case virtue first and foremost you have
to if you just think of yonis Sara's
kind of perspective then you need to kind of
of perspective then you need to kind of
get your nose out of it and that is
going to mean restraining precepts
first refinement from
there yeah so purification of views uh
sorry yes so purification of views
is not the first step MH in
the relay Chariot Su that the the SAR
was was defining the the steps of the
training and um ironically many people would
and um ironically many people would
think that you start from there mhm and
that's where you would be
endlessly uh just uh almost like going
back and forth in terms of beliefs and
opinions like you know
reintegrating um synr in and and mixing
and matching yeah and that is precisely
why it stays on the level of opinions
and beliefs and why it doesn't go
further yeah so if you you will still
have so that's the the another thing I
wanted to mention you will inevitably
you will have views and and opinions
like so that's why it's important to get
the information from the outside like
you can't uh become a Buddha by yourself
you need to to to um get that utterance
of another you'll be able to arrive at
it by yourself but
uh that's another thing like important
to recognize as well
because well without that how would you
even know for example that virtue is is
important how would you even know that
what purification of Mind entails which
is the second step how would you even
know that you're supposed to emphasize
purification of virtue which for most
people would not be the first thing that
comes to mind so you need the utterance
of another for you to even start with
these um with the graduate training with
all these prerequisites it's just that
you um you don't emphasize it past the level
um you don't emphasize it past the level
where it motivates you to do these
things like beyond that point you
realize okay I I got enough information
to recognize the importance of these
things and now the purification of you
will come if I purify my virtues
sufficiently and as a result of
purifying my virtue not as a result of
meditation techniques I purify my mind
as well and then you'll be able to see
that information that you uh obtained
initially you'll be able to see as we
say on the right level yeah because uh
it's well obviously as the Su to say
it's the five hindrances that prevent
the um seeing things as as they are
quote unquote M um so it's not um it's
not again through through concentration
practices it's you could basically boil
it down to
saying it's your way
of behaving in the world including by
mind uh
that goes against those principles that
you understand in theory that's what the
five hces are in a very broad sense
like you you you to the point where you
can even be having the right information
that restlessness is UNH wholesome
craving is UNH wholesome all these
things are UNH wholesome
but with that information you're acting
out of the five hindes that's how subtle
it is so
um but obviously you won't be able to
see that until you purify your virtue
first so that's why purification of Mind
comes second and The Graduate training
always presents in that order so but
then once those bases are covered now
you have a chance of factually even
seeing what craving means MH before that
you couldn't and again you you have to
ask yourself like so because sometimes
people have a think that okay on account
of this or other practice they were able
to see what craving is but so did it
actually require you to purify your
virtue like do you see directly that
without virtue it would have been
impossible for me to get to that point
or does it feel like if I had just you
know known one detail or another about
this the performance of this technique I
would have gone in there without any
virtue MH if if that's the case it means
it's not the purification of you at
least that's describing the sutas yeah
because as he's saying it's like it's
like you got to the to the second
Chariot without the first one uhhuh
that's literally impossible that's a
simil it givs like you take the first
Chariot it takes you somewhere but not
past that point from then on you need to
take the second Chariot who which will
take you to where the third Chariot is
yeah so if you magically were able to
jump from the first to the third that
tells you that well that that's that's
not the same training that we're that
we're talking about yeah so this kind of
this vaguely reminds me of just
something I've been sort of thinking
about the past few days um kind of using
weight loss as an
analogy how to put
this I mean take somebody who wants to
lose weight
um you you give them the option oh you
can just press this button and
automatically you'll lose weight they
they'll press it and you know a few
months down the line they'll be in the
same position they were before cuz if
you want to lose
weight you kind of actually need to
shift your goal not to losing weight but
to having a lifestyle that is conducive
to having a healthier body to having
a healthy active lifestyle essentially
so if somebody can bring themselves to
value that type of
Lifestyle more or less the issue is
solved even if they're still not at the
kind of point of weight loss that they
wanted to get to yet cuz it's about that
mode of being that's what'll actually
get you there it's not just kind of the
magical like snap of a finger oh my gosh
I'm skinny yeah even if go celebrate
with cake even if technically obviously
there isn't something that can take you
to the right view by a Moment Like even
when people think they get these
insights if you get to the nitty-gritty
details of it they're contradictory with
the sutas like it's not in line with
what the Buddha actually describes as uh
as the three characteristics what what
he describes as the five agates and so
on uh but even if theoretically it were
possible to have a momentary Insight of
that kind that is factually accurate and
then you you were to lose it well the
fact that the person wouldn't be putting the
that the person wouldn't be putting the
emphasis on the things that the Buddha
did put the emphasis on which is virtue
or like in this case the healthy
lifestyle as you mentioned means it's
not it's not actually the right here
because um like the the the the Buddha
would describe it's like AAP is not just
someone who
has wholesome
qualities is somebody who understands
wholesome is wholesome UNH wholesome is
UNH wholesome the root of the wholesome
and the root of the UN wholesome so in
other words the S is not just someone
who got thin or got Skinny It's someone
who understands the path that that uh
regardless of how fat they might be now
it will take them to be skinny at some
point so if like again it was a magical
button that they pressed there's
absolutely no
understanding uh of of what is it that
that takes you there so like so because
actually that happens like there's quite
often a view that um if you just get
like a experience of sensation of
suffering that qualifies you as a as a
stream Mentor but again that's like somebody
Mentor but again that's like somebody
who and and you don't know how it
happened you were just meditating for I
don't know intensively for a few weeks
and then this experience came up and
then you have to on top of everything
you have to ask other people to like
confirm or or or get guidance on it
meaning like again you suddenly lost 20
lbs you don't know why well that's not
that's not really um that's concerning
yeah no this this will sound like a joke
but I used to wonder if you could give
somebody stream entry with like a VR
headset and like the right kind of
program put on it like that was
something I or hallucination like you
know you bring them to Hall
hallucinatory State which is essentially
with meditative techniques you're doing
and then you kind of induce them uh make
them think about something while in
there in that hallucinatory state and
that's literally like what uh what
people would think of as you know why
you need somebody you know to then give
rise to wisdom uhuh uh but again that's
that's just a magic trick and you
haven't understood MH the root of the UN
wholesome in the sense that as we were
saying before you would be free from
doubt in regard to it and you will be
able to explain to somebody else exactly
what they would have to do in order to
get to that point and wouldn't depend on
like oh when when you're this type of
person you have to do this or when you
have this situation you have to do that
it would be on a very Universal level of
what great adversion and delusion are
which you have understood in
yourself BL you understood how you came
to that understanding yeah ex exactly so
if you were to like lose that
understanding let's say out of some
obviously that's not going to happen but
theoretically you would know exactly how
to get back to it and that's why you
actually wouldn't lose it yeah so that
Noble disciple is sort of in between PJ
and AR like he he knows how he became a
noble one that's one thing that is sort
of retrospective looking back these
things I did all right it resulted in
this right view just now being on the
path he knows if I keep doing this and
he's Beyond doubt about that that's
going to lead to the complete sensation
of suffering so this is why it's
important to organize on thinking along
those three different kinds of
understanding and not just think I'm
completely confused and one insight and
everything is going to be solved at once
yeah and and also um so because again
you you can have
that kind of assimilated and and say
yeah I do I do see that based on this
understanding if I were just repeat it I
would eventually U get to our answer but
the question is like is it something
Universal can you truly say that it's
something Universal that you understood
like that applies to absolutely every
to the point where you would have the
confidence actually when as the S would
say like there u a noble disciple would
know there is no aesthetic or Brahman in
the entire universe who could
fundamentally rightly disagree with
this that they can't accept another
teacher for that matter either yeah so
he would say it's like a like a strong
post that then you know whichever
direction the wind comes it wouldn't be
able to move
so in the same way would say the nople
would be
perfectly um established in that view and to some
um established in that view and to some
it might sound like the ultimate
close-mindedness yeah or like a
fundamental belief except that for him
it is not the long on the level of Bel
exactly so because it's again so it's
these Universal truths that you
recognize even before it's not that you
kind of developed um how to put it it's
not that you kind of
uh again it's not just that you lost
weight which is like something that you
did and that's most of the time what
people see is as mental development no
you understood the principle of losing
weight which was there always like if
you just eat less than you spend you
will lose weight so you understand that
principle and it's not that in the
past when you weigh I don't know 500 lb
that principle was not there no that
principle was operating there the whole
time so if it's not something Universal
that you understood it's like you just
understood like if I do this practice
like this in this way and you have all
this sort of system of of methods that
you bind together but there's nothing
Universal about it and most certainly
you would you would not see that this is
what everyone has to do in order to get
the stream entry yeah then that's not a
universal insight for